史之最初  这里只有黑暗
In the beginning, there was darkness,
大爆炸后  产生了时间
and then, bang, giving birth to
空间  物质
an endless, expanding existence
成为一种无止境  不断扩张的存在
of time, space, and matter.
这里充斥着惊人而极其难解的秘密
Every day, new discoveries are unlocking the mysterious,
每天  人类都有新发现
the mind-blowing, the deadly secrets
揭开这些谜团
of a place we call...
这便是宇宙
The universe.
纵贯它45亿年的历史
Throughout its 4.5 billion-year history,
我们的太阳系目睹了一场大规模屠杀
our Solar System has witnessed carnage on a colossal scale.
时不时地
Time and again,
大灾难就会粉碎行星的平静
catastrophes have shattered the planetary peace.
在正确位置的巨大撞击
A large impact striking at the right location
能够使这整个星球完全消失
could have caused the whole planet to go off kilter.
世界将被撞毁
Worlds have collided
或者变成遍布火山
or been paved over by runaway volcanism...
甚至会被撞出太阳系的范围
or even ejected from the Sun's grasp.
在太阳系这种恐怖活动的笼罩下
No planet has provided sanctuary
没有行星能够提供避难所
from the Solar System's reign of terror.
如果小行星处于高速状态下
If you have an asteroid slam in at high speed,
小块的水银将会从表面飞离出来
then little bits of Mercury will go flying off the surface,
有一些水银块不可避免会撞向地球
and inevitably, some of those chunks will hit Earth.
如果你认为地球是一个安全的避难所
So, if you think Earth is a safe haven,
那么  再想想吧
think again.
从最初的剧变  让行星成形
From the oldest cataclysm that rocked the planets,
到最终的大灾难
to the ultimate disaster
让一切灰飞烟灭
that will one day blow them to oblivion,
系好安全带  我们即将倒数回顾
fasten your seatbelts, as we count down...
改变行星的十大灾难
The ten greatest catastrophes that changed the planets.
宇                   宙
改变行星的大灾难
地球  这颗行星如今非常的平静
Planet Earth-- Peaceful today--
过去也曾经历过大碰撞
has suffered its share of collisions,
火山大喷发
massive eruptions,
以及物种大灭绝
and mass extinctions.
与太阳系其他兄弟姐妹行星
But most Earthly disasters pale in comparison
所发生的毁灭性灾难相比
with the apocalyptic traumas
地球遭受的大部分灾难显得微不足道
that befell our siblings in the Solar System.
本字幕由YYeTs人人影视 原创翻译制作
仅供学习 禁止用于任何商业盈利行为
更多影视更新 请登陆 www.YYeTs.com
翻译：sienna 小样 小冰蓝 小早 句号 木木   时间轴：sienna 阿丹
校对：月月    后期：灰灰是菇凉    总监：丢丢
太阳系诞生于大漩涡之中
The Solar System was born in a maelstrom,
数之不清的巨大石块相互撞击
as billions of rocky boulders collided
形成了我们今日所知的众多行星
to form the planets we know today.
暴力造就了太阳系
The birth of the Solar System was full of violence.
各种小行星体以及原行星
There were all sorts of planetesimals and protoplanets
相互撞击
colliding with one another
或经过另外一个时  太接近
or going close past one another
亚历克斯·菲利潘科
加州大学伯克利分校
而造成相互排斥
and ejecting each other,
而把彼此推向太阳
or sending each other down toward the Sun,
所以  只有一些行星幸存下来
so, you know, only a few planets survived.
太阳系之初  非常像
The early Solar System was very much
一场宇宙弹球比赛
like a cosmic pinball machine
这场比赛之中充斥着相互作用
where you had lots of impacts
以及相互撞击
and lots of collisions taking place,
毁灭行星  形成行星
destroying planets, forming planets,
迈克尔·密西纳
美国宇航局  喷气推进实验室
行星解体
breaking apart planets,
创造出了我们今日所见到的一切
creating everything that we see today.
但在很久以前  太阳系并不是
But long ago, it would not be the type of place
适合我们生存的地方
that we'd want to live.
当幸存下来的行星成型
As the surviving planets took shape,
这种暴力现象却更厉害了
the violence only intensified.
首先  十大行星大灾难
First, and earliest, on our countdown
排在第十位的是
of the ten worst planetary cataclysms...
第十位
水星地幔危机
the Mercury Mantle Disaster
水星  是最接近太阳的行星
Mercury, the closest planet to our Sun,
也是太阳系中最小的行星
is also the runt of the Solar System.
科学家们认为这颗弱小的行星
Now scientists think the puniest planet
却承受着宇宙最强大的冲击
was dealt one of nature's mightiest blows.
对科学家来说  水星一直是个迷
Mercury's a mystery to scientists.
水星的内核是铁
The iron core inside Mercury
大约占到了水星体积的40%
is about 40% of the volume of the planet,
比如说  在地球上
whereas on Earth, for example,
地核仅占到其体积的20%
the core is only about 20% of the Earth's total volume,
哪怕地球比水星大了三倍
even though Earth is about three times larger than Mercury.
在行星领域中  水星是一道难题
Mercury is a bit of a conundrum in planetary science.
水星就像是太阳系中的大钢球
It's like the Solar System's big ball bearing sitting out there.
丹·督答
西南研究所
几乎是纯粹的钢铁
It's almost like a pure piece of steel.
这么小的行星  密度怎么会如此高
How did that little planet get so dense?
有一个理论称
One theory holds
行星之间的碰撞就是罪魁祸首
that a planetary collision was the culprit.
但撞击为何能增加行星的密度呢
But how could an impact make a planet dense?
想象一下  撞上水星的是个大炮弹
By envisioning Mercury's cosmic attacker as a cannonball,
有助于我们理解当时发生了什么
we can help re-imagine what happened.
我们点燃美国革命中使用过的大炮
Let's fire cannonballs from this American revolution cannon
攻击40码外裹了石膏的保龄球
at a bowling ball covered with plaster 40 yards away.
现在  就把这个裹了石膏的保龄球
Now, that bowling ball covered with plaster
当做最初的水星
represents the early Mercury,
石膏就是当初水星的地幔和地壳
where the plaster is the mantle and crust.
这位是加里·哈珀  是武器专家
Now, Gary Harper, our weapons expert,
他将为我们点燃大炮
is gonna fire this cannon for us.
加里  我们该怎么做
Gary, how do we do this?
非常简单
Well, fairly simple.
我们用适量的火药来点火
We use the appropriate powder charge,
把它塞入到炮道中
insert it into the bore,
-塞进去  -好
- seat it. - Yeah.
我们把炮弹也塞进去
We take our cannonball and set that in, start it,
把炮弹塞到火药上
set that on top of the powder.
弹速会达到多少
How fast is this thing gonna go?
应该有每秒300英尺
Should be going about 300 feet per second.
那就大约有每小时20英里了
Wow. That's about 200 miles an hour--
应该有一定程度的破坏力了
Should do some real damage.
亚历克斯  现在戴上听力保护怎么样
Now, how about some hearing protection, Alex?
好的  也戴上我的墨镜  是吧
Right. And my glasses here, right?
-戴上你的墨镜  -没问题
- And your glasses. - Okay.
现在要做的就是最重要的一件事了
Now, all we have left to do is prime it,
-准备点火  -好
- and we're ready to fire. - All right.
-给大炮点火吧  -好
- Let's fire this cannon. - Okay.
-要点火了  -好
- Fire in the hole! - All right.
-打中了  -你看到了吗
- It hit! - Did you see that?
-你炸掉了  跟我击个掌  -我们做到了
- You blasted it! High five! - We did it.
我们该去看一看
We got to go take a look at that.
-对  我们一起去看看  -走
- Yeah, let's go take a look. - Okay.
到处都是石膏块
Wow, there's stuff all over the place here.
是啊  石膏层被击落
Oh, yeah, the plaster has been knocked off.
看啊
Look at that.
科学家们
This is exactly
认为水星外层就是这么剥落的
how scientists think Mercury's crust was blown away,
留下了这个铁心行星
leaving the remaining planet an iron core.
这完美地解释了水星密度怎么会如此之高
So this nicely explains how dense Mercury is.
因为大冲撞导致外壳剥落
It has this big iron core 'cause the rest of this stuff
所以就剩下了铁心
was largely stripped away by the collision.
干得真好  大炮一下就击中了保龄球
So. Good job aiming the cannon at this bowling ball.
宇宙空间中的冲撞
The celestial crack-up
使得喷射出来的水星地幔飞向太阳
would've ejected Mercury's mantle into the Sun
也飞向木星
and flung it as far as Jupiter.
这些残片漂浮了长达四百万年
The wreckage rained down for up to four million years.
这些残片散落到了整个太阳系
The debris went throughout the Solar System
有些甚至掉到了各大行星上
and could even have landed on planets.
事实上  有一些猜测
In fact, there are some estimates
多达16万亿吨的水星地幔物质
that up to 16 million billion tons
掉落到地球表面
of material from Mercury landed on Earth.
但是这种论调的支持者
But proponents of the cosmic hit-and-run theory
面临着一个两难局面
face a forensic dilemma.
如果大冲撞的确发生了
If the collision happened,
水星表面为什么没有留下创伤痕迹
why didn't it leave a visible scar on the surface?
其他关于水星铁心形成的猜想
Other ideas for the formation of Mercury's large core
考虑水星所处位置  那特有的高温环境
involve the local environment of Mercury being so hot,
由于太阳能输出量的变化
due to fluctuations in the solar output,
整个行星一直在蒸发
that the entire planet actually vaporized,
岩石构成的地幔就被汽化了
the rocky mantle actually became rock vapor,
而太阳风又将这些岩石蒸汽吹向宇宙
and the solar wind blew that rock vapor away out into space.
这又是一种解释
So that's another possible explanation
地核保留了下来  因为是由金属构成的
for why the core survived, because it was made of metal
外层岩架所经受的汽化现象
and didn't suffer quite the same vaporization
不会发生在金属身上
as the outer rocky shell did.
宇航局的信使号太空船
NASA's Messenger spacecraft is
目前正在绕水星飞行
currently orbiting Mercury,
希冀解开水星动荡过去之谜
hoping to unlock the mysteries of its turbulent past.
但遭受重创的并不仅仅是
But it wasn't just the innermost planet
这颗最靠近太阳的行星
that took a beating.
今天  土星壮丽的光环
Today Saturn's spectacular rings
安详地绕其旋转着
rotate in calm serenity,
但是它们的美丽
but they owe their beauty
源自于四十亿年前
to a makeover of the most violent kind
一次无比暴力的"化妆"
over four billion years ago.
行星灾难排名第九位
Number nine on our countdown of planetary catastrophes...
被粉碎的土星卫星
Saturn's shattered moon.
虽然土星的光环
Although Saturn's rings
是太阳系中最引人注目的奇观
are one of the most noticeable things  in the Solar System,
劳拉·丹利
格里菲斯天文台
也是太阳系中的几大谜团之一
they've also been one of the big mysteries of the Solar System.
它们是在多久以前形成的
How long ago did they form?
又是如何形成的
How did they form?
还有最让人疑惑的是
And perhaps most puzzling of all,
为什么土星标志性光环的主要成分是冰
why are Saturn's iconic rings mostly made of ice...
且重量高达33千万亿吨
33 million billion tons of it?
雕刻家罗兰·赫尔南德斯重现了
Sculptor Roland Hernandez has re-created Saturn
土星及它的一颗冰制卫星
and one of its icy moons
来帮我们展现一个新理论
to help us visualize a new theory...
一场卫星灾难
How a lunar catastrophe
如何孕育了土星光环
could've given birth to Saturn's rings.
这里是直径约60厘米的土星模型
We have a beautiful two-foot version of Saturn,
还有冰构成的卫星
and we also have its wonderful moon made out of ice.
真是太美了
It's just beautiful.
不过看上去有些奇怪
It looks a little strange, though,
这并不像我们今天熟知的土星
it doesn't look like the Saturn that we know,
因为它没有光环
because it doesn't have the rings,
但这是我们此行的目的
but that's why we're here,
因为我们想将卫星表面的冰移除
because we want to take ice off the surface of this moon
从而造出围绕土星的光环
and create rings around Saturn.
现在  很多科学家相信
Many scientists now believe
很久以前  一颗冰雪覆盖的卫星
an ancient, ice-covered moon
陷入了土星的引力束缚
fell into Saturn.
土星强大的引力
As it did, Saturn's powerful gravity
将卫星表面的冰层剥去  环绕自己旋转
pulled off the moon's ice, and swept it into orbit.
这台磨砂机充当了土星的潮汐力
This sander acts like the tidal force of Saturn,
剥掉卫星由冰层形成的地幔  形成土星环
pulling the icy mantle of this moon off and in orbit.
卫星本身冲向土星
The moon itself fell into Saturn,
无迹可寻
leaving no trace behind,
但它留下了今天我们看到的土星环
but it left the glorious rings that we see in Saturn today,
光环大多是由冰组成
which are made mostly of ice.
在土星剩余的60颗卫星当中
Of Saturn's 60 remaining moons,
泰坦星是最大的一颗
Titan is the largest.
它是月球的1.5倍大
It's 1 1/2 times bigger than the Earth's moon.
但最新的模拟模型显示
But new simulations show
土星起初有若干颗
that Saturn could have begun
更大的卫星
with several larger moons
它们都无法挣脱引力  而撞向土星
that were all lost as they helplessly plunged into the planet,
其中最后一颗形成了土星的光环
with the last moon creating the bands of rings.
这个模型第一次解释了
The model really, for the first time,
光环中冰的由来
explains the ice-rich nature of those rings.
如果单单是一颗卫星爆裂
You know, you'd expect kind of an equal mix
那么环中岩石和冰
of rock and ice and stuff
将会是一样多的
if they were just a battered, broken-apart moon,
但根据这种理论  卫星在公转中
but this whole idea that you had a moon spiral in
由冰层组成的地幔被剥离
and had its outer, icy mantle stripped off
而剩余的核心继续向土星靠近
as the rest of the core continues inward
最终形成冰制的光环
to make the rings out of the icy mantle...
土星环的起源说明
The origin of Saturn's rings illustrates
即便是最美丽的事物
that even its most beautiful features
也是从暴力中产生的
were born in violence.
上述两次灾难
But while the disasters
都仅对土星和水星带来影响
that shaped Saturn and Mercury were localized,
另一场惊天灾难将整个太阳系搞得七零八乱
one catastrophe ripped the entire Solar System apart.
不仅影响了今天我们看到的所有行星
It not only affected every planet we see today
还将很多行星抛出了太阳的引力圈之外
it even hurled planets right out of the Sun's grasp
进入了黑暗的
and into the dark exile
星际空间
of interstellar space.
巨大的宇宙灾难
Cosmic catastrophes,
如前所示  能破坏水星地幔
like the early disasters that destroyed Mercury's mantle
形成土星光环
and formed Saturn's rings,
也能塑造太阳系的方方面面
have shaped almost every aspect of the Solar System.
但现在  随着时间流逝
But now, as we move forward in time,
灾难甚至决定了
disasters even determined
行星的排列顺序
the order in which the planets line up.
今天  远离太阳
Today, traveling out from the Sun,
外部气态巨星的排列顺序是
the order of the outer gas giants
木星  土星  天王星和海王星
is Jupiter, Saturn, Uranus, and Neptune,
但曾经  情况大不相同
but once, things were very different.
在太阳系历史早期
Early in the history of the Solar System,
土星和木星围绕太阳公转的
Jupiter and Saturn kind of wandered around
轨道半径不太稳定
at different distances from the Sun,
因为它们不断地
and that's because they were continually interacting
亚历克斯·菲利潘科
加州大学伯克利分校
与剩余的小行星体相互作用
with the leftover planetesimals in the Solar System.
进而影响到它们的轨道
That affected their orbits.
木星土星公转轨道的波动
As the orbits of Jupiter and Saturn fluctuated,
引发了一些列的连锁反应
they set off a cosmic chain reaction
使太阳系大乱
that tore the Solar System apart.
终极行星灾难
Number eight in our countdown
排行榜第八位
to the ultimate planetary catastrophe...
轨道漩涡
The Orbital Maelstrom.
在木星形成的五百万年后
500 million years after the planets formed,
它距离太阳越来越近
Jupiter elbowed inwards toward the Sun,
而土星  天王星和海王星则渐渐远离
while Saturn, Uranus, and Neptune drifted outwards.
最终  木星的公转周期
Jupiter eventually orbited around the Sun
正好是土星公转周期的一半
exactly twice for every one time that Saturn did.
这一关键时刻被称为"二比一轨道共振"
This pivotal moment is known as "The two-to-one resonance."
二比一轨道共振
Two-to-one resonance
是一种强烈的引力作用
is a very strong gravitational interaction,
主宰太阳系达几百万年
when taken over millions of years,
格雷格·劳克林
加州大学圣克鲁兹分校
木星和土星的二比一轨道共振
and having Jupiter and Saturn in a two-to-one resonance
对整个太阳系造成了深远的影响
leads to profound consequences throughout the Solar System.
它扰乱了其他星球的轨道
It shakes the orbits of the other objects up.
导致了轨道交叉  可以引发大碰撞
It leads to crossing orbits, and it can lead to giant impacts.
土星和木星的引力共振
Saturn and Jupiter's resonant gravity
使天王星和海王星的轨道失去平衡
destabilized the orbits of Uranus and Neptune.
这一出行星抢椅游戏
The resulting game of planetary musical chairs
引发了太阳系规模最大
ignited the largest and most long-lasting catastrophe
持续时间最长的灾难
ever to shake the Solar System.
当木星和土星达到二比一轨道共振
When Jupiter and Saturn reached that two-one resonance,
汇聚了大量的引力势能
it imparted a lot of gravitational energy
劳拉·丹利
格里菲斯天文台
从本质上搅乱了外太阳系
that essentially stirred up the outer Solar System.
海王星和天王星被抛向更远的轨道
Neptune and Uranus were thrown into much higher orbits,
它们甚至交换了位置
and they even switched places.
现在二者的顺序是天王星  海王星
So now the order is Uranus, Neptune.
起初  顺序是海王星  天王星
In the beginning, it used to be Neptune followed by Uranus.
海王星和天王星可能不止一次
Neptune and Uranus may have switched orbits,
而是好几次交换了轨道
not once, but several times.
但它们算幸运的
But they were the lucky ones.
很多行星很可能被迫
Several planets were most likely
集体离开了太阳系
hurled out of the Solar System altogether,
注定在黑暗的
doomed to wander forever
星际空间徘徊一生
in the blackness of interstellar space.
几乎可以确定
It's almost a certainty
太阳系在这一过程中损失了很多行星
that our Solar System has lost planets along the way,
在这种天体桌球游戏中
during this sort of, uh, celestial billiards
行星交替互换位置
that's played and planets swapping places.
甚至有证据证明
There's even some evidence, perhaps,
丹·督答
西南研究所
木星和土星可能进入过
that Jupiter and Saturn may have wandered
内太阳系
into the inner Solar System,
在退回到它们当如今的轨道前
to near the position where the Earth is today,
曾经到达过今天地球的位置
before wandering back out to their present locations.
但二比一轨道共振只是一个开始
But the two-to-one resonance was just the beginning.
41亿年前  气体巨星
As the gas giants searched for stable orbits
在寻找稳定轨道时
4.1 billion years ago,
引发了一场
they ignited the most wide-ranging cataclysm
波及整个太阳系的灾难
ever to engulf the Solar System...
目前为止  依然如此
So far, anyway.
行星灾难第七位
Number seven in our countdown...
晚期大撞击事件
The late heavy bombardment.
土星和木星的轨道之舞
The orbital dance of Saturn and Jupiter
不仅搅乱了外太阳系的行星运行
didn't just throw the outer gas giants into turmoil,
还形成了影响整个太阳系的大漩涡
it also ignited a system-wide maelstrom.
土木两星外围的岩屑
The wandering around of Jupiter and Saturn
会因为引力发生聚集  形成原行星
would have created gravitational tugs on the protoplanets
这就是小行星带的起源
that were forming in the region of the asteroid belt.
互相碰撞产生的碎屑
That would have caused them to smash together,
形成了更多的小行星
shattering them into a bunch of asteroids,
这大约发生在距今41亿年前
probably before 4.1 billion years ago.
土星和木星
And then the two-to-one resonance
所产生的共振
of Jupiter and Saturn
引导着这些小行星
channeled some of those asteroids
进入太阳系内部
into the inner Solar System,
拉开了剧烈撞击期的序幕
creating the era of heavy bombardment.
每当我们仰望皓月当空
We can see the dramatic results
就能看到那次撞击造成的巨大后果
every time we gaze up at the moon.
月表大部分坑坑洼洼的环形山
Most of the scars on its pockmarked face
就是晚期撞击导致的
are the result of this bombardment,
也被称为"月球灾难"
also known as "the lunar cataclysm."
1969年  隶属美国宇航局的
Proof of this disaster was discovered in 1969,
阿波罗11号飞船首次成功载人登月
when NASA's Apollo 11 mission
揭示了这次灾难的证据
put the first man on the moon.
这是一个非常有趣的推理故事
It's a really fun detective story
我们发现的地质学证据
connecting the dynamical models
说明40亿年前
that are giving us an explanation
在内太阳系
for the geologic evidence
有一次晚期大型撞击
that we see for a late heavy bombardment
而现在可建立起动态模型  解释一切
about four billion years ago here in the inner Solar System.
我们拥有的地质学证据来源于阿波罗号
We had the geologic evidence ever since Apollo
对月球上的岩石做年代测定
and the dating of the rocks from the moon
证明了大撞击的时间
that showed this period of dates at that time.
这些坑洼痕迹告诉我们
The cratering record tells us that in various spots
在太阳系各个地方  尤其是在月球
in the Solar System, especially, for instance, on the moon,
突然间  全都遭受到
that there was a sudden increase in the number
大量天体的撞击
of really large objects slamming into the planets.
月球仅是留下了这些坑洼创伤
But while the moon merely suffered cosmetic scars,
有一个行星却遭受到了毁灭性的一击
one planet received such a cataclysmic blow,
也许使其失去了孕育生命的能力
it may have lost its ability to harbor life.
太阳系最大的灾难
Number six on our countdown
排名榜的第六位
to the Solar System's greatest catastrophe...
巨型陨石撞击火星
The mars mega-meteorite impact.
这场剧烈并遍及整个太阳系的
The tumultuous late heavy bombardment
晚期大撞击
that pounded the Solar System
发生在41亿到38亿年之前
between 4.1 and 3.8 billion years ago
它不仅仅毁灭了彗星和小行星
disrupted more than just comets and asteroids.
甚至改变了某些行星的轨道
Entire planets were thrown off course,
一架美国宇航局的空间探测器
and a NASA Space Orbiter
最近发现的证据表示
recently uncovered evidence
这些行星中的一个  大约有冥王星大小
that one of them-- a world the size of Pluto--
撞上了火星
plunged into Mars,
彻底重塑了这颗红色行星
drastically reshaping the red planet.
这确实是一次非常大的撞击
It was a very large impact that struck the planet
以一个非常低
at a very low angle,
非常斜的角度撞上火星  基本是从
a very oblique angle, and essentially skimmed off
迈克尔·密西纳
美国宇航局  喷气推进实验室
火星北半球表面一擦而过
the surface of the northern hemisphere of Mars.
可以想象成
Think of it almost as if
一把刀从一个瓜表面削过
a knife were slicing through a melon, for example.
这场撞击形成了一个洼地
The impact carved out the borealis basin,
占了火星表面超过四成的面积
which covers over 40% of Mars' surface.
这是太阳系最大的撞击坑
It's the largest impact crater in the Solar System,
其大小程度相当于整个亚洲
large enough to hold the continents of Asia,
欧洲以及澳洲总面积之和
Europe, and Australia.
在其他行星能找到撞击证据
We see evidence for impacts on other planets
因为都形成了凹地
because they form craters
几乎都是一种模式
that will follow the same sort of pattern--
完好的撞击坑  通常边缘形成圆形
nice excavated pit, usually a rim around the edge,
有时也会飞溅出一些物质
sometimes a spray of material coming out.
但这种证据在火星上并不明显
But those kinds of evidence were not clear on Mars.
这些线索不得不结合
The lines of evidence have to do
火星内部的地心引力
with both the gravity the interior of Mars
以及火星表面的地形
and the topography of the surface of Mars.
综合考虑这些因素
Those, taken together,
才发现这里曾有撞击坑
show that there was a crater,
只是坑洞边缘并不那么明显
it was just sort of sunken down on the edges.
在晚期大撞击时期
At least five huge impacts pummeled Mars
火星至少遭受到了5次巨大的撞击
during the late heavy bombardment,
但是  有一件更糟的事情
but a far worse fate was
即将发生在这颗红色行星上
in store for the red planet.
下一次大灾难
And our next catastrophe may have done more
也许就不止是削掉一大块表面
than gouge out a hefty chunk of the martian surface.
可能会改变这个行星的命运
It may have changed the planet's destiny.
排行榜第五位
Number five on our countdown...
火星磁暴危机
The Mars magnetic disaster.
探测器绕火星飞行
Spacecraft orbiting Mars reveal that the planet
发现这颗行星
carries only the faint remains
自身的保护性磁场  消失殆尽
of its once-protective magnetic field.
科学家推测
Scientists speculate that
原因在于另一次大撞击
the culprit was yet another impact,
这次使其命运发生了改变
this one with life-altering implications.
我们不是很确定
We're not exactly sure
为什么火星只有一个薄弱的磁场
why Mars has only a weak magnetic field.
一种想法是  火星曾遭受巨物撞击
One idea is that Mars was hit by a gigantic object,
使其地壳和地幔温度增高
and that heated the crust and mantle,
这就使火星内部和地幔之间的
and that decreased the temperature difference
温差变化变小
between the core and the mantle.
没有了巨大的温差变化
Without there being a big temperature difference,
就没有了对流运动
there wouldn't be convective motions,
即火星内部的翻腾运动
the churning motion in the interior of Mars.
这些一旦消失  就不可能有磁场
Without them, you don't get a magnetic field.
在地球  我们的全球磁场
On Earth, our global magnetic field
使危险的太阳粒子
deflects dangerous solar particles
偏离我们的大气层
away from our atmosphere.
但在火星  磁场非常弱
But on Mars, its very weak magnetic field
仅仅只覆盖了火星的某些地方
covers only a few regions of the planet.
致命性的太阳粒子可能将
So, deadly solar particles could have eroded away
火星的大气层破坏
much of its atmosphere.
几十亿年后
And over billions of years,
这就能侵蚀掉
you can tend to erode
大气层的主体部分
a large fraction of the atmosphere,
这就包括水蒸气  二氧化碳
and that includes things like water vapor, carbon dioxide,
甚至是温室气体
things that are excellent greenhouse gases,
这些使得火星温度变得极低
which have caused the planet to become very cold,
因此  变成了我们今日所见的火星
and hence the planet that we see today
一个又冷又干的沙漠
is a very cold, dry desert.
火星磁力消失  也许就使得
The loss of magnetism on Mars may have made it impossible
生命演化和生存的可能
for life to evolve and survive
消失在这颗寒冷贫瘠的行星上
on the frigid, arid planet.
但是有些科学家怀疑
But some scientists are skeptical
磁场的消失是由于一次巨大的撞击
that its magnetism died with a colossal bang.
可能是火星仅仅是一颗小行星
It could be that Mars is simply a small planet,
相对于地球  其内部温度降得更快
and so it lost its internal heat relatively quickly
而没有热量
compared to the Earth, and without the heat,
就只剩下一个实心的铁核
it would have a solid iron core,
就不能产生磁场
and it wouldn't create a magnetic field.
无论如何
In any case,
一旦火星失去了大气层
once Mars lost its atmosphere,
就不可能在表面产生液体水
it was unable to support liquid water on the surface
因为压力太低了
because the pressure was too low.
表面没有液体水
Without liquid water on the surface,
地表生命就无生存的可能
surface life would have perished.
38亿年前  晚期大撞击
By the time the late heavy bombardment
终于慢慢停了下来
slowly came to an end 3.8 billion years ago,
太阳系的每颗行星
every planet in the Solar System
都受到了各种各样的重塑
had received some kind of makeover.
显然的是  所有的大行星
It's very clear that all the giant planets
离最初形成的地方  都有大幅度的位移
have moved substantially from where they originally formed.
海王星明显地向外移动了
We see that Neptune clearly migrated outward,
因为它把那些更小的行星
because it picked up the smaller bodies,
拉入它的引力束缚之下
like Pluto and the other Kuiper Belt objects
柯伊伯带位于太阳系的边界
是大多数彗星的来源地
例如冥王星和柯伊伯带的星体
in its gravitational sway,
并迫使它们与自己一起公转
and pushed them out along with it.
最终  这些行星进入稳定的轨道
The planets eventually settled into stable orbits,
但现今  随着它们达到成熟期
but now, as they matured,
新一轮灾难开始从内部爆发
new catastrophes began erupting from within,
而在某些情况下
and in some cases,
这些自身喷涌出的火山
these volcanic, homegrown disasters
会来自比外太空的威胁更严峻
would exceed anything from outer space.
在太阳系形成的早期
Our Solar System was profoundly shaped
各种混乱的碰撞
by the chaotic collisions and bombardments
产生了深远的影响
that marked its earliest days,
但是  38亿年前
but as the planets finally eased into
各行星缓缓进入稳定轨道
stable orbits 3.8 billion years ago,
新的威胁出现了
new threats arose.
有时候  它们与外太空
And in some cases, they were as bad
坠落的星体一样  带来厄运
as anything bearing down from outer space.
太阳系晚期大撞击
Catastrophes in the Solar System didn't end
并不是一切灾难的终结
with the era of Late Heavy Bombardment.
亚历克斯·菲利潘科
加州大学伯克利分校
这之后灾难频发
There have been catastrophes since that time.
小行星和彗星撞击行星
Asteroids and comets can pummel into planets.
火山活动猖獗
Rampant volcanism can occur on planets.
行星上灾难
There are all sorts of ways
形式是多种多样
in which catastrophes can occur on planets.
下一场灾难给一颗行星
The next disaster gave one of the planets
做了一场不幸的整形术
an ill-fated face-lift that left it
为其留下了太阳系中最壮丽的斑点
with the most towering blemish in the Solar System.
太阳系行星灾难
Number four on our countdown
排名第四位
to the Solar System's worst disaster...
火星超级喷发
the Mars super eruptions.
火星快车号探测器
The Mars Express spacecraft
最近揭露  这颗红色行星
recently revealed that the red planet
被灾难性的火山运动
has been ravaged at least five times
摧残了至少五次以上
by episodes of catastrophic volcanism,
使得火星的地表颜色
giving Mars a unique complexion,
与太阳系其他行星不同  独一无二
unlike anything else in the Solar System.
在某些方面  火星上的盾状火山
In some respects, the shield volcanoes on Mars
与地球上的某些火山十分相似
are similar to some volcanoes here on Earth,
比如夏威夷火山
such as at Hawaii.
地表下都有一座巨型岩浆库
You've got a large magma chamber beneath the surface
向地表喷发出大量的岩浆
that's erupting lots of lava onto the surface,
形成火山
creating the volcano.
然而在火星上  这种类型的火山
However, on Mars, these types of volcanoes
比地球上的火山大10到100倍
are 10 to 100 times larger than they are on Earth.
在整个行星表面  喷发的巨型火山
So, all across the planet, you've got these eruption events
迈克尔·密西纳
美国宇航局  喷气推进实验室
遍布星球表面
that are occurring here and then here and then here,
随着时间的流逝  整个行星表面
and over time, sort of the whole surface
都被岩浆占据了
gets filled in with this lava.
火星上遍布着20座主火山
Mars is home to about 20 major volcanoes,
包括太阳系最大的火山
including Olympus Mons,
奥林匹斯山
the largest in the Solar System.
通过这座高耸的古火山
This towering relic provides
我们可洞察这颗行星火热的过去
an eerie glimpse into the planet's fiery past.
当我们翻阅火星的地质史
When we look at Mars' geologic record,
可以通过表面火山坑的数量
we can tell how old things are
格雷格·劳克林
加州大学圣克鲁兹分校
辨别其年代的久远
by looking at how many craters are on the surface.
如果表面相对年轻
If the surface is relatively young,
那火山坑的形成时间
then there has been relatively little time
相对较短
for craters to build up,
表面就呈现出平坦  无坑洼的地形
and so we see a surface that's largely flat and unmarred.
如果表面年代久远
If the surface is very old,
那我们就会看到不计其数的火山坑
then we see large numbers of craters.
因此  通过火山坑的年代
And so, through crater dating
以及火星表面的精密绘图
and through careful mapping of the Martian surface,
我们得到火星上的火山活跃期
it looks like there were perhaps five very major episodes
大约分为五个阶段
of volcanic activity on Mars.
与地球上的盾状火山一样
Just as with shield volcanoes on Earth,
火星上的岩浆库饱和
magma chambers rose to the surface of Mars,
岩浆冲至火星表面  一直喷发
broke through, and spewed basaltic lava
长达几个世纪
in centuries-long eruptions.
但是地球的盾状火山和火星的
But there was a key difference between Earth's shield volcanoes
巨型火山有本质区别
and the behemoths on Mars.
在火星上  从没有地球上那种
On Mars, there was never large-scale plate tectonics--
大规模的板块构造之说
the type that we have on Earth.
所以火星上的火山爆发时
So, on Mars, when a volcano gets going,
是非常安静的  岩浆不断从火山口涌出
it just sits there and keeps piling lava out and out and out,
形成了巨型盾状火山
and it builds up enormous shield volcanoes,
就像奥林匹斯山
like Olympus Mons.
在地球上  有板块构造
On Earth, there's plate tectonics.
比如  夏威夷的火山岛
So, for example, the volcanic islands of Hawaii
就呈现带状
are in a chain.
因为板块向北漂移
Because the plate is moving north,
而热点则相对固定
the hot spot is relatively fixed,
新的岛屿也如雨后春笋般出现
and new islands keep on popping up.
但在火星上  岛是一成不变的
But on Mars, it's the same island all the time,
只不过是面积越来越大
and it just keeps getting bigger and bigger.
大规模的火山活动一次又一次
Massive volcanism radically changed
给火星的外貌带来巨大改变
the surface of Mars time and time again.
但它不是唯一一颗
But it wasn't the only terrestrial planet
收受到内部剧烈活动影响的类地行星
that fell victim to episodes of extreme home-grown violence.
行星灾难排行榜  下一位
Next on our countdown of planetary disasters...
金星危机
The great Venus meltdown.
离地球最近的行星  金星
Our closest planetary neighbor, Venus,
在形成初期可能和地球极为相似
may have begun quite Earthlike.
两者差不多同时形成
It was born at roughly the same time
而且由相同的宇宙物质组成
and made with the same cosmic materials,
但某场灾难将金星变成了
but something transformed Venus
地球的恶魔双子星
into Earth's evil twin.
如果穿透金星厚厚的大气层
If you could penetrate through its thick atmosphere,
就会发现90%的金星表面
you'd see that about 90% of the surface of Venus
都被早起火山活动产生的固态熔岩覆盖
is covered by solidified lava from previous volcanism.
而厚重而有害的大气
And the thick, noxious atmosphere
主要由二氧化碳组成
consists mostly of carbon dioxide,
而金星的大气压
and it has an atmospheric pressure
大约是地球表面大气压的90倍
about 90 times that on Earth's surface.
这就与水面下九百多米
That's like being 3,000 feet
受到的压力差不多
below the surface of the ocean.
两者感觉是相同的
That's what you'd feel.
此外  金星的温度
Moreover, the temperature on Venus
接近五百摄氏度
is nearly 900 degrees fahrenheit.
这种极端的高温足以使铅融化
That's huge. It's enough to melt lead.
所以  如果人类突然出现在金星表面
So, if a human were suddenly placed on the surface of Venus,
会被瞬间烤熟
he would be baked
然后被压成碎片
and very quickly totally crushed.
金星表面地狱般的环境
The hellish conditions on Venus could have been caused
可能是由于30亿年前
by an extreme runaway greenhouse effect
失控的温室气体效应造成的
over three billion years ago.
如果金星起初有海洋的话
So what happened to the oceans of Venus,
那海洋到底怎么了
if they were there to begin with?
当太阳逐渐放亮
Well, the Sun gradually grew brighter,
造成海洋水大量蒸发
and that led to more evaporation of the oceans,
致使大气中水蒸气含量增加
increasing the water vapor content of the atmosphere.
而水蒸气是温室气体
Well, water is a greenhouse gas,
这个过程也就使得气温剧增
so that led to a greater increase in temperature,
从而导致更多水分蒸发  更多温室气体形成
which led to more evaporation, more greenhouse gases,
失控的温室效应
a runaway greenhouse effect
最终蒸发掉了金星海洋里所有的水分
that eventually evaporated away the oceans of Venus.
海洋消失的证据
Evidence of these lost oceans
也许隐藏于金星的云盖上方
may exist above the cloud decks of Venus.
从金星大气样品的分析得知
We know from sampling Venus' atmosphere
一种叫做氘的重氢
that there is a high concentration of the form of
其浓度极高
heavy hydrogen called deuterium.
大多氢逃逸到宇宙中
Most of the hydrogen escaped to space,
只有少量重氢留在大气层中
and the small dregs of hydrogen that did remain
也就是氘
are this special heavy form called deuterium.
气候巨变会对行星产生重大影响
Venus provides a great example of what can happen to a planet
劳拉·丹利
格里菲斯天文台
而金星就是很好的例子
when the climate changes dramatically.
如果我们能弄清楚金星上发生的一切
If we are able to understand what happened on Venus,
就可以之为鉴  防患于未然
we can apply those lessons learned here on Earth.
若一场生态灾害
If an eco-disaster
将金星表面的液态水全部汽化
evaporated the liquid surface water on Venus,
那么生命体是否也全部罹难了呢
were there living creatures that also perished?
一位观众向节目组提出了此疑问
That's what one viewer wanted to ask the universe.
观众提问
来自德克萨斯州沃思堡的杰克·科肖
So Jack Kershaw from Fort Worth, Texas,
发信来问
emailed us...
金星上真的曾有生命存在吗
Did life once thrive on Venus?
杰克  这问题真问的不错
Jack, that's a really fascinating question.
在金星生命的首个十亿年中
It turns out that Venus may have had oceans
海洋很可能覆盖了金星的部分表面
for the first half billion or billion years of its existence.
如果真是这样
If so, primitive life,
也许在这些海洋中  曾形成过
by which I mean microbes and bacteria,
低等生命形式  即微生物和细菌
may have formed in those oceans.
只是我们未可知
We just don't know.
而在地球上  低等生命形式
But on Earth, primitive life formed
在晚期大撞击后不久  就出现了
shortly after the end of the late heavy bombardment.
如果金星也是如此
If the same thing happened on Venus,
那必定孕育过生命
then Venus once had life.
观众提问
根据温室效应理论
According to the greenhouse theory,
经过数百万年的逐渐演变
the surface of Venus became bone-dry gradually
金星表面变得极干燥
over millions of years,
但并非所有人都认同此观点
but not everyone agrees.
一些科学家驳斥道  金星上的水
Some scientists argue that the water on Venus
事实上并不是一点点蒸发的
actually disappeared not slowly,
而是消失于一场灾难中
but in one disastrous day.
在所有袭击太阳系的灾难中
Of all the catastrophes that have swept the Solar System...
金星的遭遇也许是最令人不解的
perhaps the most puzzling is what happened to Venus.
她原本是一个气候温和的类地行星
A planet originally so warm and Earthlike,
也许还曾孕育过生命
it might have harbored life.
几十年来  科学家们认为
For decades, scientists theorized
一种失控的温室效应
that a runaway greenhouse effect
使金星表层平均温度缓慢上升
slowly raised the planet's average temperature
至灼热的460摄氏度
to a scorching 860 degrees fahrenheit--
几乎是水星表层温度的两倍
almost double that of Mercury.
但地球的这颗邻居
But Earth's next-door neighbor
其毁灭之路也许另有一条
may have taken a different road to ruin.
一种能让金星
One way that Venus may have lost
一下子失去大量水分的方式是
a substantial chunk of its water all at once
遭受巨大的冲撞
is through a giant impact.
庞大的天体撞击金星
A giant impact will hit the planet,
导致大面积的金星表层脱离
basically strip off a huge amount of the outer layer.
并且产生了巨大的能量
That provides an incredible amount of energy,
格雷格·劳克林
加州大学圣克鲁兹分校
巨大的热量
an incredible amount of heat,
因而易挥发的元素  如水  氨或甲烷
and so volatile elements, like water or ammonia or methane,
极易流失到星际空间
are simply lost to interplanetary space.
当发生巨大的行星冲撞
And after the giant impact has occurred,
万物消逝之后  只剩下
after everything has died down, you're left with a planet
一颗干燥的
that's much drier and made of material
由气化温度较高的物质组成的星球
that has a much higher vaporization temperature.
该理论的拥护者们声称
Proponents of the theory
冲撞的力量是如此巨大
claim the cosmic punch was so powerful,
甚至将行星的自转轴撞歪了
it actually spun the planet off its axis.
金星的自转方向
Venus spins in the direction
与大多数行星相反
opposite that of most of the planets,
对此我们并不知其原因
and we don't know quite why that is,
亚历克斯·菲利潘科
加州大学伯克利分校
但已知的是  在太阳系形成早期
but one idea is that it was hit by a gigantic object
金星曾受到一颗巨大物体的撞击
early in the history of the Solar System,
根据撞击方式的不同
and that effectively either flipped it
金星被撞得改变自转方式
or just reversed the sense of rotation,
或者直接被撞翻过去
depending on exactly how the object hit Venus.
金星的命运告诫着人们
The fate of Venus is a telling reminder
地球温和的气候环境
that even temperate conditions, like those on Earth,
是来之不易的
can never be taken for granted.
若你还不认同这一点
If we didn't know that already,
本次行星灾难排行榜的第二名
number two in our countdown of planetary catastrophes
是最有力的证据
drove the point home.
这次灾难  全世界都目睹了
And this time, the whole world was watching.
苏梅克-列维九号彗星撞击事件
The Shoemaker Levy 9 impacts.
我们以前总认为
We used to think that
外太阳系的行星都很稳定
the outer planets were pretty stable.
劳拉·丹利
格里菲斯天文台
它们不会遭受什么事情
There wasn't a lot happening to them.
但事实上  如今我们总会看到这些行星
But in fact, now we see impacts hitting the outer planets
遭受撞击
all the time.
最大的气星  木星
Jupiter, the largest gas giant,
已然成为公认的太阳系活靶子
has been our Solar System's planetary punching bag.
它强大的引力场足以吸引彗星
It's gravitational force deflects renegade comets
奥尔特云是一个假设的包围者太阳系的球体云团
布满着不活跃的彗星
使脱离它们位于奥尔特云
that break loose from their orbital prisons
与柯伊伯带的运行轨道
in the Oort cloud and Kuiper belt.
木星受到撞击的几率比其他任何行星
The rate of impacts on Jupiter is greater than that
都要大的多  原因有两点
of any other planet, for two reasons--
第一  木星是最大的行星
first, Jupiter is the biggest planet,
因而它的横截面最大
so it presents the biggest cross section.
更容易被撞到
Things are more likely to hit it.
第二  木星质量非常大
Second, Jupiter has a huge mass,
因而它会吸引天体靠近
so it pulls objects in toward it.
从某种意义上来说  木星是自找麻烦
In a sense, Jupiter is asking for trouble.
木星承受过许多次严重的撞击
Jupiter has taken a lot of nasty hits,
包括人类观察到的最剧烈的
including one of the most violent celestial catastrophes
一次天体撞击
ever witnessed by mankind.
1994年7月
In July, 1994,
全世界都目睹了21枚彗星碎片
the world watched as a chain of 21 comet fragments
以毁天灭地之势
raced towards the giant planet
对木星发动了连环撞击
and struck it with colossal force.
苏梅克-列维九号彗星以其发现者命名
Shoemaker-Levy 9, named after its discoverers,
它的这次撞击
delivered the energy
与六万亿TNT爆炸相当
of six million mega tons of TNT.
苏梅克-列维九号撞上木星时
During the Shoemaker-Levy 9 impact on Jupiter,
彗星碎片以每秒数十公里的速度
you had this ripped-up comet coming in
一个接一个撞上木星
at tens of kilometers per second
并在木星大气层发生爆炸
and impacting Jupiter in one airburst after another,
与此同时  木星还在自转中
as Jupiter spun underneath the comet.
因此  彗星碎片所造成的撞击
And so that led to a series of impacts being spread
沿着某一纬度分布
along a particular latitude of Jupiter's surface
所造成的痕迹
and leaving these scars,
完全可以使用地面望远镜进行观测
which were visible in telescopes from the Earth.
由于木星表面是气态的
The fragments didn't produce craters,
所以这次撞击并没有产生环形山
because Jupiter doesn't have a solid surface.
相反  它们对木星致密的大气产生撞击
Instead, they struck the gas giant's dense atmosphere,
使得大气内部的物质喷发出来
dredging up material that erupted
留下了一串喷发口
in a trail of venting scars.
撞击的痕迹  就像乌云一般
The impact scars, the dark cloud features,
与地球的尺寸相差不大
were about the size of our planet Earth,
这一事实验证了一个说法
and that tells an important tale,
丹·督答
西南研究院
那就是  如果有一枚
that if you have an object that's, you know,
直径八百米左右的星体撞击地球
a half a mile across striking an object the size of the Earth,
那么由撞击所产生的尘埃
the dust pall from that impact
将会覆盖整个星球
will encompass our entire planet.
我们从木星的撞击上学到的是
So that's the lesson we learned from the Jupiter impacts,
地球历史上的一些撞击
is it really brought home the story of impacts
是如何发生的
right here on Earth.
在木星表面的深色印记的观测期
The dark imprints left on the cloud decks of Jupiter
仅仅为几个月
were only visible for several months,
随后它们就消逝在木星湍急混乱的大气中
before being mixed into its turbulent atmosphere.
木星的大气活动
Jupiter has very vigorous
异常的活跃  常会出现极端气候
and, oftentimes, very violent weather patterns.
因此  虽然彗星爆炸的威力巨大
So, no matter how destructive that airburst might be,
在几周到几个月之间
over a period of weeks to months,
气流  也就是木星的气旋
the currents, the airflow in Jupiter's atmosphere
逐渐控制住外来物
takes the pollutants
并使其扩散到整个大气表面
and disperses them through the planet.
这次灾难性撞击的证据
And the evidence for the catastrophic impact
也随之消散不见
dissipates and disappears.
苏梅克-列维九号撞击提醒着我们
Shoemaker-Levy 9 is a scary reminder
太阳系中仍流窜着彗星
of the cosmic unrest in our Solar System,
但科学家称最终极的灾难
but scientists warn that the ultimate catastrophe
还没有到来
still looms in the future.
至于地球
And for Earth,
将在劫难逃
there can be no escape.
我们的太阳系
Our Solar System has weathered
已在改变行星命运的灾难中
over four billion years of
挣扎了超过四十亿年
planet-altering catastrophes.
有些时候  影响甚为明显
In some cases, the effects are obvious,
如晚期大撞击
like the craters
所留下的环形山
of the late heavy bombardment that
使月球凌乱不堪
still litter the moon.
而在其他行星上  这些证据早已毫无踪迹
In others, the evidence has long since disappeared.
不过科学家们最近发现了
But scientists recently discovered
灾难排行榜上的第二名
that number two on our countdown of catastrophes
引起了让他们从未想象过的连锁反应
has created a ripple effect they never imagined.
美国宇航局最近对比了  从卡西尼号
NASA has recently compared images of Jupiter
卡西尼号是土星探测器
和新视野号上拍下的木星图像
from the Cassini and New Horizons missions
新视野号是木星探测器
其发现令人大吃一惊
and made a stunning discovery.
和土星一样  木星也有光环
Like Saturn, Jupiter also has rings,
尽管看起来微弱多了
though much fainter.
可是有些事让他们很不安
But something has disrupted them.
当你仔细看木星的光环
If you look at the rings of Jupiter,
会发现实际上是有褶皱的
they actually have little corrugations,
呈现出起伏
little ripples in them,
这些起伏是光环的某部分
and those ripples are formed
丹·督答
西南研究所
发生倾斜而产生的
when a portion of the ring is tilted
然后随着它继续不断旋转和形成
and then as it continues to spin and evolve over time,
这些起伏向外扩张
those ripples wander out,
沿着光环传播开来
propagate out through the ring system.
如果分析这个光环
If you unwind that system
并倒推这些起伏的产生时间
and work back out the ripples,
你会知道
you can find out
整个光环的平面是什么时候
the point in time when that ring plane
开始倾斜的
had gotten tilted over.
光环开始倾斜的时间
That point when that ring got tilted
正好是在1994年7月份
was right around July of 1994.
1994年7月份是
July, 1994 marks the date
苏梅克-列维九号彗星撞击事件的时间
of the Shoemaker-Levy 9 impact event.
科学家们有了一项重大发现
The scientific sleuths had made a key discovery.
彗星碎片撞击木星主体时
As the cometary fragments struck Jupiter itself,
细小的碎片穿过了它的光环
much smaller debris passed through its rings,
使它们发生倾斜与扭曲
tilting and twisting them
从而变成了我们今天看到的起伏
into ripples that we still see today.
像苏梅克-列维九号彗星
In the case of a disrupted comet
这种分崩离析的彗星
like Shoemaker-Levy 9,
你看到的是一整团尘埃
you've got an entire pall of dust,
一团巨大的物质
a large mass of material
在整个光环的平面上分散开来
distributed across the disk of the rings,
落于各个角落
raining through that system.
因此  不单是一两个光环组成体被换掉
And so, rather than displacing only one or two ring particles,
而是一整片都被换点  使光环倾斜
you can do the entire cloud at once, tipping on the side.
苏梅克-列维九号彗星并非是
Shoemaker-Levy 9 wasn't the only comet
近期唯一在木星上留下痕迹的
to leave its calling-card mark on Jupiter in recent times.
2009年7月  另一颗小行星
In July, 2009, another asteroid
猛撞在巨型气体行星的南极附近
smashed into the gas giant near its south pole.
当它冲击木星后  溅出了大气深处的
When it impacted Jupiter, it brought up a lot of material
大量物质
from deep within the atmosphere
并在行星表面留下了一个巨大的伤疤
and created a huge scar on the surface of the planet
迈克尔·密西纳
美国宇航局  喷气推进实验室
几个星期都不会消退
that was visible for many weeks.
这个黑灰云团的规模
The size of this black ash cloud
可能等同于地球上的太平洋
was perhaps the size of the pacific ocean on the Earth.
相当庞大
It was quite large.
人们预测  每隔十到十五年
It's now estimated that an asteroid or comet
木星会被小行星或彗星撞击一次
hits Jupiter every 10 to 15 years,
是地球被撞击几率的五千倍
which is 5,000 times higher than the rate of impacts on Earth.
我们观测到了好多次
The fact that we've seen several of these
这暗示撞击一直存在着
suggests that it's happening all the time,
劳拉·丹利
格里菲斯天文台
因为我们并不能观察到所有的
because there are all the ones we don't see.
在外太阳系的气体巨行星上
So there's a lot more impact activity
发生的撞击活动  比想象中的多
on the outer gas giants than we ever thought.
如果木星不在我们的太阳系中
If Jupiter was not in our Solar System,
那么地球将变成
the Earth would be essentially a sitting duck
向太阳前进的所有碎片  彗星
for all the debris, the comets and the asteroids
以及小行星的撞击目标
that were falling in towards the Sun,
而地球所遭受到的无尽灾难
creating vastly larger numbers of catastrophes on Earth
将绝不止现在这么多
than we've experienced through our history.
随着太阳系逐渐成熟
But as our Solar System ages,
新的威胁似乎也出现了
new threats will likely arise,
地球也将面对一场宇宙终极审判
and Earth itself will face a cosmic day of reckoning
就连木星也无法阻止
that nothing, not even Jupiter, can prevent.
也就是灾难排行榜上
Which brings us to number one
位列第一的那一场...
on our countdown of catastrophes...
行星末日
Planetary armageddon.
许多科学家相信
In several billion years,
在数十亿年内  最大的行星木星
many scientists believe Jupiter, the largest planet,
和最小的水星
and Mercury, the smallest,
将会在轨道争夺上对抗
will face off in an orbital duel,
而一位无辜的旁观者  地球
and an innocent bystander, Earth,
却正好位于集火的中心
just might find itself in the line of fire.
现在的太阳系可以说是
Right now our Solar System
非常按部就班地在运行着
is kind of the paradigm of clockwork regularity,
格雷格·劳克林
加州大学圣克鲁兹分校
可事实证明
but it turns out that, you know,
行星之间的万有引力会相互影响
the planets do affect each other gravitationally.
长时间看来  行星的轨道
The planetary orbits are, over very long periods of time,
会来来回回地摇摆和旋转
vibrating in and out and turning.
木星和水星的公转步伐将被协调至
Jupiter and Mercury will begin to turn their orbits
相同的比率
at the same rate,
一旦事成定局
and if that happens,
水星的轨道将会日益愈发偏离日心
Mercury's orbit becomes progressively more eccentric.
会日益变得狭长起来
It becomes progressively more elongated
直到最终  轨道的远日点
until the point where, at its far point from the Sun,
与金星轨道交叉
it's actually crossing Venus' orbit.
一旦水星的的轨道
If Mercury's orbit ever gets to the situation
与金星的轨道相交
where it's crossing Venus' orbit,
那么后果不堪设想
then basically all hell can break loose.
科学家们已经计算出
Scientists have calculated
四种灾难后果中的每一种
one of four disastrous consequences.
水星可能与太阳碰撞
Mercury might collide with the Sun,
可能被驱逐出太阳系
might be ejected from the Solar System,
可能猛撞金星
might smash into Venus...
或者最坏的情形是
or in a worst-case scenario,
水星可能会和地球相撞
Mercury might collide with the Earth,
炸毁我们的地幔和大气
blasting away our mantle and atmosphere
使地球变成不毛之地
and sterilizing our planet.
目前我们从电脑模拟中得知
As far as we can tell from computer simulations,
水星成为脱缰之马的几率
there's about a 1% chance
大约是百分之一
that Mercury's orbit will go haywire.
而在这百分之一的几率中
And within that 1% chance,
就有地球遭水星撞击
there's a small probability that things will unfold
这样的小概率事件
in such a way that the Earth itself is impacted by Mercury.
水星绝不是我们在太阳系里
Mercury is hardly the only threat we face
面对的唯一威胁
from within the Solar System.
根据一些场景模拟
According to some scenarios,
火星同样面临轨道混乱的未来
Mars also faces orbital chaos in the future.
而它  同样也可能撞向地球
And it, too, may slam into the Earth,
重演月球经历过的浩劫
repeating the disaster that gave rise to the moon,
而不仅行星会如此
and it's not just planets.
周期性靠近的天体  会影响到
Nearby stars periodically disrupt comets
奥尔特云中的彗星  从而使它们
in the Oort cloud, which could send them
成为太阳系中自杀式行动的一份子
on a kamikaze mission through the Solar System
并引发一场新的太阳系晚期大撞击
and set off a new late heavy bombardment.
而若像众人预料的那样
And if, as most expect,
仙女座星系最终与银河系相撞
the Andromeda galaxy ultimately collides with the Milky Way,
银河的连环撞击
the galactic pileup could
会粉碎太阳系伪装下的平静
shatter our Solar System's deceptive calm.
最终的行星之灾
The ultimate planetary catastrophe,
我认为还没有发生
I think, is still in our future.
灾难  在太阳系的历史中
Catastrophes have always played
一直扮演着一个暴力而重要的角色
a violent, yet vital, role in our Solar System's history.
没有它们  我们的邻居将会是另一番天地
Without them, our neighborhood would be a very different place.
通过研究这些反复无常的活动
By learning about these volatile events,
我们能更好的理解  它们是如何
we can better understand how they helped
形成我们赖以栖息的星球
form the planet that gave us life
以及怎样才能保护地球与人类
and how we might protect it and us
免遭未来的灭顶之灾
from the catastrophes of the future.